Finding Aid for Juris Upatnieks papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Juris Upatnieks papers
1963-1994
1965-1979
Upatnieks, Juris.
2013062 Aa 2; UAl
Papers of Juris Upatnieks, a University of Michigan scientist who helped to lay the foundations of holography, a photography technique that recreates the recorded objects with all of their three-dimensional optical properties. Collection includes Upatnieks correspondence with American and international scientists and companies, scientific papers, proposals and technical reports, sometimes prepared in collaboration with other scientists, as well as digitized laboratory notebooks and lantern slides illustrating his research on various subjects.
7.25 linear feet in 7 boxes
1 oversize folders
453 MB online
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donated by Juris Upatnieks (Donor no. 10919 ) in April 2013 and December 2013.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Juris Upatnieks was born in Riga, Latvia, in 1936. The family immigrated to the United States in 1951. Upatnieks received his Bachelor of Electrical Engineering degree from the University of Akron in 1960 and Master of Science in Engineering, Electrical Engineering degree from the University of Michigan's Institute of Science and Technology in 1965. Between 1960 and 1972 he worked at the University of Michigan Institute of Science and Technology Willow Run Laboratories, where he held positions from Research Assistant to Research Engineer. In 1962 he and the University of Michigan professor of Electrical Engineering and the Willow Run Laboratories Research Associate Emmet Leith recorded the first transmission hologram of a two-dimensional object (a photographic transparency or slide). Leith and Upatnieks published results of their work on holography in Fall 1963, publicizing it as "lensless photography." They continued working on improvement of their technique using newly available laser to achieve coherence of light and clear three-dimensional holographic images. In December 1963 the first three-dimensional object was recorded. Results of their work in this area were presented in 1964 and caused renewed interest to coherent optics, holography, and their practical applications in medicine, optics, data storage, airline safety, space science, the military, the arts, among other fields. Upatnieks reflected on reviving the field of Holography in his work "Development of Holography: from November 1962 to January 1965" (1965)
Between 1973 and 1993 Upatnieks worked at the Environmental Research Institute of Michigan and was an Adjunct Professor, Electrical and Computer Engineering Department at University of Michigan. From 1993 to 2001 he consulted as Senior Engineer for Applied Optics research and development laboratories in Ann Arbor, Mich. Throughout his professional life Upatnieks has collaborated on research projects with faculty members of the University of Michigan Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science and Department of Mechanical Engineering and Applied Mechanics. Upatnieks has received twenty U.S. patents, for ten of which he is the sole inventor.
Juris Upatnieks is a fellow of the Optical Society (OSA) and of the Society of Photo-Optical Instrumentation Engineers, and foreign member of the Latvian Academy of Sciences. In 1975 Upatnieks was awarded the R. W. Wood Prize by the Optical Society of America. In 1976 he was named Inventor of the Year by the American Association for the Advancement of Invention and Innovation and received the Holly Medal by the American Mechanical Society. In 1999 the Latvian Academy of Science awarded him the Grand Medal for contributions of development of the principles of holography and for promoting its use. Upatnieks was awarded the Walter Cap Prize in 2007 from the Latvian Academy of Sciences and the Latvian Patent Office and Emmett N. Leith Medal in 2010 from the Optical Society of America. Juris Upatnieks is listed in "Who's Who in America."
The collection documents Juris Upatnieks' scientific research and output and divided into six series: Correspondence, Subject Files, Proposals, Reports, Lantern Slides, and Laboratory Notebooks.
Subjects:
Upatnieks, Juris.; Holography--Research.; Laboratories--Michigan.; Research--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Environmental Research Institute of Michigan.; University of Michigan. Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.; University of Michigan. Institute of Science and Technology.; Willow Run Laboratories.
Contributors:
Leith, Emmett N.
Genre Terms:
Lantern slides.
- Correspondence and Memoranda (Box 1)
  The Correspondence series (0.75 linear feet) includes correspondence and memoranda for the years 1963-1981 and 1988. Upatnieks' correspondence includes exchanges with American and international scientists discussing scientific research and experiments, as well as manuscripts and published work. The majority of memoranda are Upatnieks' communications on the subject of ongoing research addressed to his colleagues.
  - Correspondence, 1963-1981; 1988; 19 folders (Box 1)
- Subject Files
  The Subject Files series (1 linear foot and oversize folder; 1963-1991) consists of Upatnieks' files dedicated to specific areas of research and activities, manuscripts drafts and printed copies of articles and research papers, often accompanied by correspondence with publishers and notes, and texts of conference presentations. The oversize folder contains blueprints related to Upatnieks' work with the Exxon Foundation. Subject Files are dated between 1967-1968 and 1972-1982.
  - Exxon Foundation, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Exxon Foundation blueprints, 1973 (Folder 1)
  - Holograph sight, 1972-1976 (Box 1)
  - Holographic scanner, 1978-1982 (Box 1)
  - Light-line sight, 1976-1977 (Box 1)
  - Major, R. W., 1982 (Box 1)
    (includes photographs)
  - NASA grant, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - Synthetic Target System, 1977-1978 (Box 1)
  - Air Traffic Control Displays, 1970 (Box 7)
  - Articles and research papers files
    (by Upatnieks)
    - 1963-1966 (Box 7)
    - 1967 (Box 7)
    - 1968 (Box 7)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 7)
    - 1973-1974 (Box 7)
    - 1980s-1990s (Box 7)
  - Articles, collected (Box 7)
  - Bibliographical References (Box 7)
  - Book Reviews, 1969 (Box 7)
  - Conferences and professional meetings
    - Electro-Optical Systems Design Conference, 1969 (Box 7)
    - Expo, 1967 (Box 7)
    - National Academy of Sciences, 1967 (Box 7)
    - Holography and Computer, 1969 (Box 7)
    - International Commission for Optics, 1969 (Box 7)
    - International Optical Computing Conference, 1975 (Box 7)
  - Diffractive Optics (ERIM), 1991 (Box 7)
  - Laser Technology in Aerodynamic Measurements Lecture Series, 1971 (Box 7)
  - Optical Society of America
    - Meetings with gaps, 1966-1976; 7 folders (Box 7)
    - The Efficiency and Image Contrast of Dielectric Holograms, 1970 (Box 7)
  - University of Michigan Engineering Summer Conferences Courses
    - 1967 (Box 7)
    - 1969 (Box 7)
    - 1972 (Box 7)
- Proposals
  The Proposals series (0.3 linear feet) is arranged chronologically and then by proposal title within each year. The majority of material are technical proposals, but a number of management and financial proposals are included. Also included here a number of concept papers.
  - Concept papers
    - A Concept for a Compact Aircraft HUD, 1985 (Box 1)
    - Compact Sight for Use with Night Vision Goggles, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Multiple Fourier Transform HOE, 1988 (Box 1)
    - Diffraction Gratings for Pulse Stretching and Compression, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Airborne Laser Receiver Using Diffractive Optics, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Compact Holographic Sight for Use with Soldier Integrated Ensemble, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Compact Holographic Sight for Small Arms, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Spatial Frequency Magnification without Lenses, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Construction of an 11"ร14" Back-reflection Type Hologram, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Investigation of an Unaided Stereo Display, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Three-dimensional Display of Air Traffic, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Investigation of Coherent Imaging Systems, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Investigation of Holographic Optical Elements, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Construction of Holographic Displays for Educational Purposes, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Diffraction Optics Study, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Investigation of Holographic Light-Line Sight, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Display Hologram, 1976-1977 (Box 1)
  - Construction of a Synthetic Target System, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Investigation of Holographic Data Storage in Dichromated Gelatin, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Nap-of-the-Earth Display System, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Holographic Scanners, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Development and Fabrication of a light-line Helicopter Sight, 1982 (Box 2)
  - Compact Coherent Optical Correlation and Matched Filter Maker System, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Grating-based Optical Microlithography for Mimic Applications, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Production of Holographic Optical Elements: Proposed Concept for NASA Solicitation, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Holographic Automative Displays, 1991 (Box 2)
- Reports
  The Reports series (1 linear foot) includes activities, semiannual and final project reports prepared by Juris Upatnieks by himself and/or in cooperation with his colleagues. This series is divided into subseries: Environmental Research Institute of Michigan (ERIM), Institute of Science and Technology (IST), Holotron Corporation, Manuscripts, and U.S. Army. Within each subseries material is organized in chronological order. The majority of material are technical reports. A number of IST reports were prepared by Upatnieks in cooperation with his colleagues, notably with Emmett N. Leith. The majority of ERIM reports were prepared by Upatnieks but some bear names of Upatnieks' colleagues. Manuscripts include drafts of scientific papers and lectures. Memoranda contains reports on ongoing research: descriptions of experiments, findings, further steps, etc. The U.S. Army subseries includes printed reports and papers.
  - Environmental Research Institute of Michigan (ERIM)
    - 1970s, 2 folders
      - 360ยบ Hologram Camera and Display System for Educational Use, May 1975 (Box 2)
      - Holographic Light-line Sight Experimental Model: Operating Manual, November 1976 (Box 2)
      - Optical Spectral Analysis of Extraterrestrial Data: Final Report, April 1977 (Box 2)
      - Holographic Scanners as UPC Label Readers for the POS System: Final Report, October 1977 (Box 2)
      - Holographic Scanner Study: Final Technical Report, October 1978 (Box 2)
      - Design and Test of Breadboard Synthesized Target System (STS), November 1979 (Box 2)
    - 1980s, 3 folders
      - Holographic Scanners and Related Technologies: Final Technical Report, January 1980 (Box 2)
      - Holographic Scanners and Related Technologies: Final Technical Report, March 1981 (Box 2)
      - Holographic Scanner Copying: Final Technical Report, October 1981 (Box 2)
      - Brassboard Coherent Optical Correlator and Filter Maker: Final Technical Report, October 1982 (Box 2)
      - Sensor Design Concepts for Machine Vision Systems: Internal Research and Development Report, May 1983 (Box 2)
      - Image Quantifier Design Study: Technical Report, April 1984 (Box 2)
      - Results of Phase II Effort Preliminary Experiment of the BIIQ System Study: Report, June 1984 (Box 2)
      - Optical Processing Technology review and Assessment: Final Technical Report, July 1984 (Box 2)
      - Doctor-blade Coating and Processing of Dichromated Gelatin Plates: Internal Research and Development Report, April 1985 (Box 2)
      - Investigation of a Holographic Helicopter Sight: Technical Report, May 1985 (Box 2)
      - Brassboard Holographic Helicopter Sight: Final Report, June 1986 (Box 2)
      - Compact Coherent Optical Correlator System: Final Report, May 1988 (Box 2)
      - Design and Fabrication Approaches for Compact Optical Processors Using Diffractive Optics: Internal Research and Development Report, September 1989 (Box 2)
    - 1990s
      - Production of Holographic Optical Elements, 1990 (Box 2)
      - Holographic Displays for Automobiles: Internal Research and Development Final Report, January 1992 (Box 2)
      - Optical Pulse Compression Gratings: Internal Research and Development Report, January 1992 (Box 2)
      - Planar Optics Technology Development, October 1992 (Box 2)
    - Activities reports, 1982-1992 (Box 2)
    - 1960s, 4 folders
      - A Study of Holographic Compensation of Lens Aberrations, January 1966 (Box 2)
      - Optical Processing Techniques: Semiannual Status Report, December 1967 (Box 2)
      - Investigation of Hologram Techniques, January 1968 (Box 2)
      - Investigation of Hologram Techniques: Final Report, June 1968 (Box 2)
      - Optical Processing Techniques: Final Report, October 1968 (Box 2)
      - Investigation of Hologram Techniques: Interim Report, April 1969 (Box 2)
      - Investigation of Hologram Techniques: Interim Technical Report, July 1969 (Box 2)
      - Investigation of Holographic Testing Techniques: Semiannual Technical Report, August 1969 (Box 2)
      - Holographic Displays: Final Report, September 1969 (Box 2)
  - Institute of Science and Technology (IST)
    - 1970s, 3 folders (Box 3)
      - Investigation of Holographic Testing Techniques: Semiannual Report, April 1970 (Box 3)
      - A Study of Hologram Recording and Applications: Interim Technical Report, July 1970 (Box 3)
      - Investigation of Holographic Testing Techniques: Semiannual Report, September 1970 (Box 3)
      - Investigation of Holographic Testing Techniques: Semiannual Report, February 1971 (Box 3)
      - Investigation of Holographic Display Techniques: Final Report, May 1971 (Box 3)
      - Investigation of Holographic Display Techniques: Final Report, December 1971 (Box 3)
      - Investigation of Hologram Techniques: Final report, July 1972 (Box 3)
    - Progress Reports of Juris Upatnieks, December 1960-September 1972 (Box 3)
  - Holotron Corporation
    - Correspondence, 1966-1969 (Box 3)
    - Progress Reports for Holotron, 1966-1969 (Box 3)
    - U.S. Army Armament Com, 1977 (Box 3)
    - U.S. Army Missile Com, 1978-1979; 1981-1982 (Box 3)
  - Manuscripts
    - Recording of Color Images on Ordinary Film, August 1967 (Box 3)
      (draft)
    - Holography and its Applications: Practice of Holography--How Do You Do It?, 1968 (Box 3)
      (lecture)
    - Holography: NEC Course Notes, 1970 (Box 3)
    - Holographic Displays, October 1971 (Box 3)
    - Hologram Visual Displays, undated
  - Memoranda
    - Addressed to others (scattered years), 1966-1994 (Box 3)
    - Administrative, 1963-1968 (Box 3)
    - Consulting, 1973-1980 (with gaps) (Box 3)
    - Memoranda to file
      - 1965-1988, 7 folders (Box 3)
      - 1990-1992 (Box 3)
  - U.S. Army
    - U.S. Army Armament Com, 1977 (Box 3)
    - U.S. Army Missile Research and Development Com, 1978-1979 (Box 3)
    - U.S. Army Missile Com, 1981-1982 (Box 3)
- Lantern Slides
  The Lantern Slides series (3 linear feet) contains glass slides with images, tables and graphs.
  - Applications (Box 4)
    - Recording retina (Box 4)
    - Multiple images on one hologram (Box 4)
    - Data recording demo (Box 4)
  - Historical slides and basic holography (Box 4)
  - Noise suppression in coherent imaging (Box 5)
  - Noise suppression with phase moderation (Box 5)
  - Random phase-moderate transparency and untitled (Box 5)
  - Recording materials, dielectric, etc. (Box 6)
  - Recording math and materials (Box 6)
- Laboratory Notebooks
  The Laboratory Notebooks series (3 notebooks and 453 MB online) contains digitized versions of Juris Upatnieks's laboratory notebook from January 16, 1963 to December 2, 1982. The notebooks record variables, procedures, and results of experiments related to hologram construction, photography, microscopy, and optics among related topics. Includes Upatnieksโs analyses of results, equations, hand drawn renderings of optical set ups and photographic examples of holograms.
  - 1963-1965 (Box 3)
  - 1965-1968 (Box 3)
  - 1968-1982 (Box 3)
  - 1963-1965, .PDF and .ZIP files
  - 1965-1968, .PDF and .ZIP files
  - 1968-1982, .PDF and .ZIP files
Related Collections
Emmett N. Leith papers, ca. 1936 and 1954-2005 at the Bentley Historical Library. Finding aid is available online.